JOSHUA COOK: Hi, my name is Joshua Cook,
and I'm a curriculum developer with Databricks.
Today, we're going to be talking about latent semantic analysis.
There is a link to the notebook I'll
be using in the video description
if you would like to follow along.
Before we begin, let's define some basic vocabulary.
Natural language processing refers
to a family of techniques that are
used to derive meaning from text data.
A document refers to some collection of words
and represents the rows or instances of our data set.
A body is a collection of documents
and represents the entire data set.
A dictionary is the set of all words
that occur in at least one document in the data set.
A topic is a collection of words that co-occur.
In this lesson, we're going to be talking about latent semantic
analysis.
So the word latent means hidden, and in this context
refers to features that cannot be directly measured.
What we're going to be measuring or what has already
been measured are the words that are in our data set.
What we're interested in is latent features, hidden features,
that represent something essential in the data set.
Latent semantic analysis is a natural language processing
technique, as well as an unsupervised learning
technique, this as opposed to supervised learning.
So in supervised learning, we would have a target or a label.
With latent semantic analysis, we don't have this.
We're looking at something that's latent or inherent
to the data itself.
The aim of latent semantic analysis is to create representations
of the text data in terms of these topics or latent features.
A side benefit of this is that we're
going to be able to reduce the dimensionality
of the original text-based data set.
As you can see in this diagram, latent semantic analysis
consists of two steps.
The first step is to generate a document term matrix,
and the second step is to perform a singular value decomposition
on that document term matrix.
The basic idea of a document term matrix
is that text documents can be represented
as points in Euclidean space.
You might know these as vectors.
Here is an example of a document term matrix.
As you can see, each row in this matrix
represents one of our documents.
In this case, one of four simple sentence fragments.
And then each column represents a word from the dictionary.
That is, a word that shows up in at least one
of the four documents.
If you look at the first row, the quick brown fox,
you can see that the word brown has the value 1,
the word fox has the value 1, the word quick has the value 1,
and the word the has the value 1.
And everywhere else is zeros.
So here we see these four documents as vectors.
As you can see, the quick brown fox is 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0, 1, 0.
The second step in a latent semantic analysis
is to do a singular value decomposition on the document term matrix.
The singular value decomposition is similar to a principal component
analysis, if you're familiar with this statistical technique.
It's going to reduce the dimensionality of the original data set
by encoding it using these latent features.
With latent semantic analysis, these latent features
represent topics in the original text data.
In the next few videos, we're going
to be looking at building a latent semantic analysis
using the open source Python library scikit-learn.
First, we'll look at a trivial implementation
using these four sentence fragments that we just looked at.